Guide to the David Brion Davis Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Brion Davis papers
1949-2016
MS 1790
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
56.67
(112 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, teaching files, lecture notes, writings, research files, program files, personal papers, and student recommendations of David Brion Davis, historian and professor of history at Cornell University, 1955-1969 and Yale University, 1969-2001.
Davis, David Brion, 1927-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Brion Davis, 2001 and 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
Student recommendations in the original accession are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
Course materials and portions of the research files in Accession 2017-M-0002 contain student records and are restricted until 2091 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
Yale University files in Accession 2017-M-0002 are restricted until 2048 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives. Personnel records in the Yale University files are restricted until 2073 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
All other materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
David Brion Davis was born February 16, 1927 in Denver, Colorado to Clyde Brion and Martha Davis. He received a BA from Dartmouth College in 1950 and a PhD from Harvard University in 1956. Davis was a professor in the history department at Cornell University from 1955 to 1969 and a professor of history at Yale University from 1970 until his retirement in 2001. Davis died on April 14, 2019.
Davis's scholarship focused on the history of slavery and abolition in the western world. While at Yale University, Davis taught courses in history, served as an academic advisor, and served as the founding director of the Gilder Lehrman Center for the Study of Slavery, Resistance, and Abolition, established in 1998.
Davis is the author of numerous monographs on slavery and abolition, including the Problem of Slavery in Western Culture (1966, and winner of the 1967 Pulitzer Prize for General Non-Fiction); the Problem of Slavery in the Age of Revolution (1975); Inhuman Bondage: The Rise and Fall of Slavery in the New World (2006); and the Problem of Slavery in the Age of Emancipation (2014). Davis also authored numerous shorting writings and essays, particularly as a regular contributor to the New York Review of Books.
In addition to his teaching and writing work, Davis participated in and held leadership roles in professional organizations, including serving as the president of the Organization of American Historians from 1988 to 1989. Davis is a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Antiquarian Society, and the American Philosophical Society.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, teaching files, lecture notes, writings, research files, program files, personal papers, and student recommendations of David Brion Davis, historian and professor of history at Cornell University, 1955-1969 and Yale University, 1969-2001.
Davis's research activities, centering on the history of slavery and abolition in the western world, are documented in the research files and writings. The writings also document Davis's work as a cultural critic and contributor to scholarly and popular publications, including the New York Review of Books. Davis's teaching activities at Yale University are documented in his teaching files, lecture notes, and student recommendations. His broader professional activities are documented in the program files, personal papers, and correspondence, which primarily pertains to requests for feedback on the written work and academic activities of his colleagues and students.
Historians -- United States -- 20th Century; Slavery; Slavery -- Antislavery movements; Davis, David Brion, 1927-; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History
- Original accession, 1970-1999; Accession 2001-M-081
  Scope and Contents
  The original accession consists of correspondence, course files, lecture notes, writings, topical files, and student recommendations.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The student recommendations are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  - Conferences files, course materials, correspondence, 1970s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vita and correspondence, 1972-1997 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
  - Topical files, including Yale History Department files, 1970s-1990s (Box 4)
  - Course materials, 1970s-1990s (Box 5)
  - Writings and research files, 1970s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Student recommendations, 1970s-1990s (Box 7–13)
    The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
- Additional materials, 1949-2016; Accession 2017-M-0002
  This accession comprises teaching and research files, writings, correspondence, and program files documenting David Brion Davis's work as a historian of slavery and abolition in the western world and professor of history at Yale University. The teaching files document Davis's teaching activities and lectures at Yale University and other educational institutions. Writings document Davis's monographs and short writings, particularly his essays and reviews for the New York Review of Books, as well as scholarly and popular writings of others that were sent to Davis for review or comment. Correspondence primarily documents Davis's professional and research activities, and correspondence is also present throughout the research files, writings, and program files groupings. Program files include material documenting conferences Davis attended and contributed to and activities Davis undertook in the professional organizations to which he belonged. The program files also document Davis's activities as founding director of Yale University's Gilder Lehrman Center for the Study of Slavery, Resistance, and Abolition and as a Yale history professor working with researchers, undergraduate students, and graduate students at the university. The accession also contains Davis's personal papers, which document his early academic work as a student at Dartmouth College and Harvard University, his written reflections on his life and work, and his professional activities and retirement.
  Researchers should note that the research and teaching files often include correspondence and writing material related to the research or teaching filing topic.
  Arrangement
  The accession is arranged under six headings: Teaching files, Writings, Research files, Correspondence, Program files, and Personal papers.
  - Teaching files
    - Course material
      The course materials are student records, which are restricted until 2091 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
      - History 161, Intellectual History, 1971-1994, undated
        - Ideas and material for planning (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Library reserve lists (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Syllabi and packets (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Intellectual history, theory, and definitions (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Introduction and Ben Franklin (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Sections discussion questions (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Class folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Lecture outlines (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - History 437B, Slavery and Anti-Slavery (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      - History 447B, 1994–1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - History 143B, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Religious Revivalism, 1985–1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - "Seeking the Big Picture" on slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - History 143A, Origins, Significance, and Abolition of New World Slavery, 1997–1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - History 447B, Last lecture class, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Cornell American history survey, 1960–1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - June seminar, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Summer course, 2000 July (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Summer seminar, 1996–1999 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
      - Summer slavery course, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Summer slavery course, 1996–1997 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - Summer course students, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Graduate reading lists and library lists, including "Slavery" list (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Graduate reading seminar, 1992–1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Slavery course planning, 1995–2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Exams, 1995–1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Slides - descriptions, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Coming of the 20th Century, 1964-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Examinations and questions, 1965–1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Intellectual history, first term, 1965–2003 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Intellectual history, second term, 1964–1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Dewey and Veblen, 1967-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Materialism, Watson, Santayana, Naturalism, and Aestheticism, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Socialist alternatives, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Junior seminar
        - Notes on readings and class notes, 1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - History 426a, Power, Influence, and Identity, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - Evaluations, past syllabi, 1977–1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Notes on reading and class notes, past years, 1977-1982, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - Slavery and Antislavery, 1985–1993 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
      - Slavery and Antislavery, 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Hiroshima debate, 1986–1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - History 710a, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - History 710b, 1995–1998 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
      - History 447b, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Graduate Reading Seminar reading notes, 1988–1999 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
      - Graduate Research Seminar records, 1974–1995 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Evaluations, 1987–1992 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Assorted and unidentified course material, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
    - Lectures
      - Notes
        - Exodus, Colonization, and Promised Lands, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Introduction, Sisterhood and Slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Public lectures, 1989, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Wilber Lecture, 2006–2007 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Origins of New World Slavery lecture, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Toni Hahn Davis talk and birthday, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Bender, anti-slavery debate, 1993-1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - Bender, anti-slavery debate, student work, 1993–1998 (Box 99, Folder 13)
          Includes student records, which are restricted until 2091 as established by Yale Corporation regulations. http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
        - Jews and Blacks, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        - Martin Luther King, Jr., 2004 (Box 7, Folder 9)
        - Pittsburgh and Williamsburg, 1993, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
        - Harvard, Mannheim, 2006 September (Box 7, Folder 11)
        - Baron Lecture, American Antiquarian Society, 2007–2008 (Box 7, Folder 12)
        - American Historical Association, Chris Brown, abolition, et alia, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 13)
        - College of Charleston, Lowcountry conferences, 1995–1997 (Box 7, Folder 14)
        - South Carolina, Charleston Lecture and Rutgers, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 15)
        - Cult of Domesticity, 1986–1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
        - Romanticism and Transcendentalism, 1980, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Live lectures, 1984-1986, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - American myths and icons in Europe and America, 1987–1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1981 December (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
        - London, 2007 April (Box 8, Folder 6)
        - Keynote, Slavery, Sex, and Dehumanization, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 7)
        - Berkeley, Jefferson Lecture, 2004 November (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
        - Davis paradigm, bondage, liberation, time, and morality, 1988, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 10)
        - W. W. Cook Lectures, Michigan, 1985–2006 (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
        - Tanner Lectures, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
        - Edited Tanner Lectures crucial for the Problem of Slavery in the Age of Emancipation, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Lecture planning, 1995–1998 (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - Exodus, Black Colonization, and Promised Lands, 1991–1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - Eric Foner, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Original Cook Lectures, copy, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - Constitution and Slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 9, Folder 6)
        - Amistad Lecture, Mohonk Mountain House, Second Judicial Circuit, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 7)
        - New York Public Library Organization of American Historians comments, 2003 April (Box 9, Folder 8)
        - Emory lecture sources, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 9)
        - Thirteenth Amendment, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 10)
        - Emory, David Eltis Lecture on Slave-Trade Abolition, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        - PBS documentary, Richard Karz, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 12)
        - David B. Davis Lecture Series, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 13)
        - Mark Weitzman, New York City book launch, 2014 (Box 9, Folder 14)
        - Notecards, 1979, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
        - Library of Congress, Hillel Group, and Adelphi talks, 1995–2004 (Box 9, Folder 16)
        - Bard College, William Wilberforce, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 17)
        - Washington, D. C., Paul Finkelman, 2006 April (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - Columbia University, 2004 June (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - Koerner Center, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Inhuman Bondage, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Koerner, Historiography of Slavery, 2009 April (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Guyana trip, 1974–1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Indiana University, 1981–1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Emancipation Moment, 1982–1983 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Westminster College, 1985 November (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Outside advisers, Baruch conference, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - Gilder-Morgan, New York City project, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        - Speaker introductions, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - Gilder Lehrman Institute course, slavery debates, 2002 June (Box 10, Folder 13-14)
        - Utah, Weber State, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 15)
        - Southern Historical Association in Little Rock, Kenneth Stampp, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 16)
        - Amistad, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - Slavery lectures, summer global course, 1993–1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - Pomona College, Fall 2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Summer lectures on slavery, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Huggins Lectures, 2002, undated (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
        - Antislavery debate, University of California, 1990–1992 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Audiotapes
        Includes recordings of Davis's lectures for specific courses and topics. Also includes one recording of Davis speaking at his home on an unidentified topic.
        - Disillusion and the Fragmentation of the Progressive Spirit, 12 April; 1 (Box 73)
        - Fundamentalism, The Great Red Scare, 19 April; 1 (Box 74)
        - Fundamentalism II, Relative and Social Values, 22 April; 1 (Box 75)
        - Fundamentalism III, Dayton as a Case Study, 24 April; 1 (Box 76)
        - History 375, 8 May; 1 (Box 77)
        - History 377, Emerson, 1967 October 4; 1 (Box 78)
        - History 377, First lecture, 1968 September 16; 1 (Box 79)
        - History 377, Violence in American Life, 1967 September 27; 1 (Box 80)
        - History 377, 1967 October 11; 1 (Box 81)
        - History 378, The 1930s, 26 April; 1 (Box 82)
        - History 378, George Santayana, the Skeptic as Pietist, 1968 February 14; 1 (Box 83)
        - History 378, Efficiency, Technocracy, and Reform, 6 March; 1 (Box 84)
        - History 378, Freudianism, 1968 February 21; 1 (Box 85)
        - History 378, The Impact of Science and Henry Adams, Reinhold and Niebuhr, 1 May; 1 (Box 86)
        - History 378, Lecture on John Broads Watson, High Priest of the Great Twitch, 1968 February 12; 1 (Box 87)
        - History 378, Materialism, Paradoxes, and Problems, 7 February; 1 (Box 88)
        - History 378, Naturalism in the Arts, 1968 February 16; 1 (Box 89)
        - History 378, Niebuhr II, 3 May; 1 (Box 90)
        - History 378, Response to Science, Anticipations of History, 13 March; 1 (Box 91)
        - History 378, Response to Science III: Critics and Defenders, 18 March; 1 (Box 92)
        - History 378, Science and the Dilemmas of Atomic Power, 8 April; 1 (Box 93)
        - History 378, The Torment of Secrecy, 3 April; 1 (Box 94)
        - Mark Twain, Fall 1967; 1 (Box 95)
        - Recording, Salisbury, Connecticut, at home, 1951; 1 (Box 96)
        - Response to Science, Anticipations of History Part II, 15 March; 1 (Box 97)
    - Evaluations and recommendations
      The evaluations and recommendations are student records, which are restricted until 2091 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
      - Senior essay reader reports, Circa 1980s-circa 2010 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Recommendations, Circa 1980s-circa 2010 (Box 12, Folder 2-5)
      - Recommendations, Circa 1980s-circa 2010 (Box 13, Folder 1-8)
      - Summary notes on essays, dissertations, and theses, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
      - The Life and Work of Clyde Brion Davis essay, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Writings
    - Essays and short writings by Davis
      - Feminist Revolution, 2000–2003 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Feminism, "The Other Revolution", 2000 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - New York Review of Books
        - Anthony Appiah, 2011 (Box 14, Folder 3)
        - Mormons, 1980–1992 (Box 14, Folder 4)
        - Eugene Genovese essay, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - Many-Headed Hydra, 2000–2001 (Box 14, Folder 6)
        - Davis notes on Andy Delbanco, 2012 (Box 14, Folder 7)
        - David W. Blight and R. J. M. Blackett, 2000–2002 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Revolution, Davis and Peter Hinks New York Historical Society essay, 2010–2012 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Papers and essays on slavery, racism, and reparations, 1987–2002 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Essays and reviews on slavery, abolitionist rhetoric, and the American revolution, 1998–1999 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - "American Dilemma," Andrew Hacker, Underclass, 1992–1994 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Jews and slave trade responses to New York Review of Books, 1994–1995 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - The New England Quarterly, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - David Brion Davis PhD thesis notes, early proposal on homicide in American Fiction, 1955–1957 (Box 16, Folder 1)
        Includes thesis critiques and review by Howard M. Jones.
      - Liberator, Prospectus, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Anthology, Davis essays for Yale University Press, 1999–2002 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Mannheim essay, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - USA Weekend magazine piece, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Journal of the Early Republic, "Jim Doc" and racial polarities, 1997–1999 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Arming Slaves volume, 1999–2003 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Encyclopedia project, Stan and Seymour Garland, 1993–1996 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Econocide, Davis preface, 2009 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Essay, Pedro Marques and Seymour Drescher, 2008 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Oxford University Press Davis blogs, 2006 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Comparative slavery paper, Organization of American Historians, 1997–1999 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - New York Times essay, The Enduring Legacy of the South's Civil War, Graduate Employees and Students Organization slavery at Yale essay, and related papers and correspondence, 2001–2005 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Slave Revolts and Abolitionism Seymour Drescher volume, 2009 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - The Family and Boundaries, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Books and reviews by Davis
      - Book reviews, unidentified short writings, and news clippings, 1958–1976 (Box 17, Folder 8-10)
      - Book reviews, unidentified short writings, and news clippings, 1985–1990 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
      - Manuscript reviews, 1962–1994 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Book reviews, 2008 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Reviews and clippings on slavery and antislavery, 1984–1988 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Seymour Drescher and David Ryden "Decline", 2010 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Davis reviews of writings by Hugh Thomas and Robin Blackburn, 1997–1998 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - The Problem of Slavery in the Age of Emancipation
        - Book outlines, 1980s (Box 19, Folder 1)
        - Chapter outlines, 1995–2006 (Box 19, Folder 2)
        - Corrected copy of Cook lectures, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 19, Folder 3)
        - Current ideas, thoughts, 2007–2009 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Description of project, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - Early thoughts, planning, 2005–2007 (Box 19, Folder 6)
        - Ideas, "war sublimated," and hegemony, 1979–1985 (Box 19, Folder 7)
        - Reading material, 2003–2007 (Box 19, Folder 8)
        - Notes, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - Overview, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - Past planning, 2006 (Box 19, Folder 11)
        - Planning, 1981–1988 (Box 19, Folder 12)
        - Race, surveys, themes, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 19, Folder 13)
        - Reviews, et cetera, 2014 (Box 19, Folder 14)
        - Schedule projections, 2008 (Box 19, Folder 15)
        - Summary, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 19, Folder 16)
        - Chapter 1
          - Draft, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 19, Folder 17)
          - After chapter 1, 2007 (Box 19, Folder 18)
          - First emancipations, freedom and dishonor, 1988 October (Box 19, Folder 19)
          - Loose notes, 2008–2009 (Box 20, Folder 1)
          - New material and correspondence, 1987–1994 (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
          - Notes on animalization, 1991–1997 (Box 20, Folder 4-5)
          - Original material, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 20, Folder 6)
          - Research, 2008 (Box 20, Folder 7)
          - Sketches and outlines, 1993–1996 (Box 20, Folder 8)
        - Chapter 2
          - Loose notes, 1986–1988 (Box 21, Folder 1)
          - New material, 1996–2003 (Box 21, Folder 2)
          - Old revisions, 2008 (Box 21, Folder 3)
          - Outlines, 1984 (Box 21, Folder 4)
          - Philipp's comparison, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 21, Folder 5)
        - Chapter 3
          - Drafts, 2006 (Box 21, Folder 6)
          - Drafts, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 21, Folder 7)
          - Sources and anticipations of racism, 2002–2004 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
        - Chapter 4 outlines and drafts, 2006 (Box 22, Folder 3)